(upbeat music)
- Hello, everyone, and
welcome to EnglishPod.
My name's Erica.
- And I'm Marco.
- So Marco, how are you doing today?
- I'm great, I'm really happy to be back,
ready to deliver another great
podcast for all our listeners.
- That's right, and we've got
an intermediate lesson today
about spending money.
- Yes, specifically spending
money in a company.
- That's right, we're going to be listening
to a business meeting as a company
describes how they're spending money.
- Right, and they're
actually looking at their profit
and loss statement, so
that's kind of interesting.
- Well, Marco, can you tell us a little
bit about a profit and loss statement?
- Yeah, sure, well, all companies come out
with a profit and loss statement every year
or every three months,
and it's basically a document
that shows all the money
that the company is spending
and all the money that
the company is earning.
- So it's a document
that outlines how much
money the company makes
and how much it expands.
- Right, so in the
end, basically it'll tell
you we're making money
or we're losing money.
- Okay, so we're going to be listening to
some people discuss a
profit and loss statement
in just a moment, but before we do that,
it's time for vocabulary preview.
- Very vocabulary preview.
- Okay, great, so today on our vocabulary
preview, we have two words for you.
So let's take a look at the first one.
- Expenses.
- So expenses are things that you
have to spend money on regularly.
- Right, so for example, in a company,
regular company expenses
are salaries or office
supplies or the phone
bills, internet bills.
- Okay, and maybe in a household or a
family your expenses might be your food,
perhaps your transportation
or your rent or your heating bills.
- So these are all things you
spend money on regularly.
They're expenses.
- Expenses, great.
Let's take a look at our
second word, through the roof.
- Through the roof, through
the roof, through the roof.
- So when something is through
the roof, it's really, really, really high.
- Really high.
- So for example, we can talk about
gas prices or through the roof lately.
- Yeah, that's totally true.
Gas prices have gone really
high in the past couple of months.
- So when we talk about through the roof,
it means that the number is really high.
- That's right, we typically
use this word with numbers.
It also gives you the idea that
the number has risen really quickly.
- Yeah, exactly.
- Okay, so through the
roof, through the roof.
- All right, Marco, do you
think it's time for the dialogue?
- Yep, let's listen to the dialogue.
As always, the first
dialogue is gonna be a little
bit fast, so it might
be a little bit difficult,
but don't worry if you
don't understand everything
because we will explain all of
the key language in a minute.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, so now the last
point on our agenda.
Jill, let's go over the
profit and lost statement.
- Great, well, the main
issue here, as you can
see, is that our expenses
are through the roof.
- Let's see, these
numbers are off the charts.
What's going on here?
- Well, the company expenditures on
entertainment and travel are out of control.
Look at these bills, for example.
Just this month, we've paid
over $20,000 for hotel charges.
- Okay, thank you, I'll look into it.
- The list goes on and on.
Here, this is a bill for
$5,000 for spa treatment.
- Thank you, that will
be all I'll take care of it.
- Look at this one, sir.
$8,000 were expensed in one
night at a place called Wild Thing.
- Okay, I get it.
Thank you for your very thorough analysis.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, so this accountants,
she's a pretty thorough, hey?
She's really persistent about her job
and the manager apparently
is a little bit embarrassed.
- Hmm, I wonder why that could be.
- Well, we'll talk about
that in a little while.
Why don't we take a look at
her language takeaway for today?
- Language takeaway.
In today's language
takeaway, we're going to look
at three words and the
first word is expenditures.
- Expenditures.
- Expenditures. - Expenditures.
- So expenditure sounds
pretty close to expenses, right?
- It's pretty similar, but it
has a little bit of a difference.
So why don't we listen to some
examples and see if we can understand?
- Example one.
- If elected president, I will increase
expenditures on health and education by 12%.
- Example two.
- We really need to control
our travel expenditures.
From now on, all managers
will fly economy class.
- Example three.
- Because of the rise in oil prices,
expenditures on food are
higher than they have ever been.
- So expenditures is the total amount of
money that you're spending on something.
- Right, that's the total amount of money.
Versus expenses is the things
that you spend money on.
- Okay, that's really clear.
Our next word is out
of control, out of control.
- Out of control.
- So when something is
out of control, it's crazy.
- Crazy, you can't control it.
- Exactly, you can't stop it.
- You can't stop it.
- Out of control.
- Okay, great.
Now let's take a look at
our last word for today.
Go over.
- Go over.
- So go over is a pretty simple word.
Why don't we listen to some
examples so we can understand, go over.
- Example one.
- I need to go over this report one last
time to make sure there are no mistakes.
- Example two.
Can you help me go over my presentation?
I wanna make sure it's perfect.
Example three.
Let's go over these numbers one more
time and make sure there are no mistakes.
- Yeah, this is a really common word
and it basically means look at carefully.
- Yeah, or review.
- In English, we often
find simple little words
they fit together really well
and you think, oh, they're so easy.
Like the word go over, so easy.
- Yeah.
- But it's the way that they interact
with each other that makes them--
- Or it makes you sound much better.
- Exactly, so go over in this case.
We might say, let's go over the lesson.
- Let's go over the lesson.
- Yeah, that sounds great.
- Yeah, and that's a more natural
way of saying something like that.
- Okay, so we've taken a look at
our language takeaways for today.
I think it's time to listen to
the dialogue one more time.
- And this time the dialogue will be slower
so we can understand and listen
to all the words we just talked about.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, so now the last
point on our agenda.
Jill, let's go over the
profit and loss statement.
- Great, well, the main
issue here, as you can see,
is that our expenses are through the roof.
- Let's see, these
numbers are off the charts.
What's going on here?
- Well, sir, the company
expenditures on entertainment
and travel are out of control.
Look at these bills, for example.
Just this month, we've paid
over $20,000 for hotel charges.
- Okay, thank you, I'll look into it.
- The list goes on and on.
Here, this is a bill for
$5,000 for spa treatments.
- Thank you, that will be all.
I'll take care of it.
- Look at this one, sir.
$8,000 were expensed in one
night at a place called Wild Things.
- Okay, I get it.
Thank you for your very thorough analysis.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, so I got it.
- Yep, it's clear now.
- Yeah, and you know, I heard
a lot of really great phrases
in this dialogue, but I'd like to
look at now in Fluency Builder.
Fluency Builder.
- Great, so today on Fluency
Builder, we have three words for you.
Let's start by looking at the first one.
Off the charts.
- Off the charts.
So this word is very similar to the roof.
- Exactly, it also means really high.
- Right, so let's listen to some examples
of how we can use off the
charts in a different situation.
- Example one.
- Oil prices have gone up
and our costs are off the charts.
- Example two.
- Excellent job, Susan.
Your sales are off the charts this year.
- Example three.
- Our losses are off the charts.
That's it, no bonuses for anyone.
- So Marco, do you think I can change
off the charts for through
the roof in these examples?
- Yeah, you can, definitely.
You can use off the charts or through
the roof, both of them mean the same thing.
- Okay, so two ways of saying
really, really, really high, really high.
But they're very commonly
used in a business setting.
- Yeah, that's true.
- Okay, so this next word
is a phrase that you can use
if you want to tell
somebody that you'll check
something or you'll
investigate something.
- Right, and we heard it in our
dialogue, so let's listen to the clip.
- I'll look into it, I'll look into it.
- So look into that, that
means I'll check something.
- Yeah, I'll see what's happening.
- Yeah, does it mean
you're gonna take action?
- No, it doesn't.
- Okay, so I think we've got another word
that does mean you're going to take action.
- I'll take care of
it, I'll take care of it.
- So this word means that you're
going to do something about it.
- I'll take care of it, I
will take responsibility.
- Exactly, so I will do something about it.
We'll investigate and I'll do it.
- Yeah, again, two great phrases.
I'll look into it, I'll take care of it.
- Okay, so now let's listen
to the dialogue a third time.
It's gonna be at its normal
speed, but now you have
all the tools you need to
understand it a lot better.
- Okay, so now the last
point on our agenda,
Jill, let's go over the
profit and lost statement.
- Great, well the main issue here,
as you can see, is that our
expenses are through the roof.
- Oh, let's see, these numbers are
off the charts, what's going on here?
- Well, the company expenditures on
entertainment and travel are out of control.
Look at these bills, for example.
Just this month, we've paid
over $20,000 for hotel charges.
- Okay, thank you, I'll look into it.
- The list goes on and on.
Here, this is a bill for
$5,000 for spa treatment.
- Thank you, that will
be all, I'll take care of it.
- Look at this one, sir.
$8,000 were expensed in one
night at a place called Wild Thing.
- Okay, I get it.
Thank you for your very thorough analysis.
(upbeat music)
- Well, Marco, I guess one of the benefits
of being an executive and a company,
especially a large companies,
you get a lot of amazing benefits.
- Yes, when you are a
manager or a CEO of one of
these big companies, you
get a lot of great things,
like I don't know, a private jet, maybe.
- Wow, that's nice.
(laughs) - Or the company
often pays for your house.
- Yep.
- Or for your car, they'll
give you a company car.
- Mm-hmm.
- They'll pay for your kids or your
children's tuition for high school.
- So there are school fees?
- Yeah, yeah. - Okay.
- And also, I've heard
about entertainment bonuses.
- Yeah, so you can go out to a restaurant,
get the receipt and claim
the expenses at work.
- Those are some great benefits, right?
- So, Marco, I'm curious to know
what our listeners' expenses are.
- Yes, we definitely want to know
what crazy expenses you have.
For example, well, let's see,
my spending on Coke Zero
has gone through the roof
since we started this podcast.
- Yes, you spend a lot of money
on Coke Zero's every week, right?
- Yeah, I probably have
a, I don't know, 10 a week.
(laughs)
- Well, for example, I spend
a lot on DVDs each week.
I usually buy two or three movies.
- That is off the charts.
- That is off the charts for DVD spending.
So we want to know what
you spend your money on.
Be sure to go into our community website
and tell us what you spend money on.
- That's right, you can
find us at www.EnglishPod.
com and Marco and I are always there to
respond to your questions and comments.
- Great, so we'll see you there.
And until then, it's, goodbye.
(upbeat music)